So far we have been looking at bandit algorithms
right or the immediate reinforcement learning
and so what we are going to start from today
is looking at the full reinforcement learning
problem right.
So we know little bit already about the full
RL problem right so what are the complications
that we are going to insert here States we
already looked at states in contextual bandits
right temporal dependence right the sequential
nature of the problem is something that we
are going to introduce here so what we are
going to look at is that we will assume that
there is a there is an environment okay and
an agent
interacts with the environment, the agent
interacts with the environment at any point
the agent senses the state the environment
is in okay.
Then in response to that the agent takes a
action which is then applied to the environment
okay so the agent senses the state the environment
is in that is St and it takes an action that
gets applied to the environment and as a result
of applying this action environment changes
to a state S t plus 1 which then gets fed
back into the agent as the current state St
and then you keep doing this in a loop right
so this could go on indefinitely or there
could be a well designated stopping state
right if you reach that state you stop the
trials okay or a group of states I mean you
can always this is this trick right.
So when I say there is a starting state and
a stopping state, it could very well be a
group of starting states and a group of stopping
states I can always define a dummy state to
which all the states go to right so I can
always say that there is a single starting
state and a single stopping state right so
that for ease of exposition so I will keep
saying that makes sense and even if there
are multiple states where you will stop I
can insert one dummy state and say that automatically
as soon as you reach one of these states you
will make a transition to the dummy state
and you will stop there okay.
So there will always be a one-stop state and
one start state right so that might happen
and apart from this
you also get a reward signal from the environment
okay this is like I was mentioning earlier
this is a convenience a modeling convenience
that we put the reward in the environment
okay that is because we want to put the reward
in a place which is outside the agent's direct
control right agent should not just arbitrarily
say okay I okay I am getting a reward of five
now right.
So it should get this reward as a result of
the behavior in the world okay it cannot just
arbitrarily set its own rewards okay so that
is the reason we put the reward in the environment
okay so that it is outside in reality right
this will be a very much more complex picture
right because if you think about it I mean
I have been repeatedly saying that all biological
agents are reinforcement learning agents right
humans are reinforcement learning agents so
do you have a separate reward conduit right.
We have a reward sensing mechanism somewhere
right so you only have what you sense from
the world right so you look around you see
whatever is whatever inputs that are coming
in whether you are in you could be ingesting
food, you could be looking at the outside
world right somebody might be touching you
on the skin whatever right so you are taking
in all these complex sensory inputs and other
kinds of actual physical ingestible inputs
okay and then you are converting them into
rewards right so that is how the rewards happen
right.
So if you are hungry and you eat okay that
is that is rewarding right but then you find
out that you have I do not know eaten something
that is gone stale right that is not rewarding
it is in fact opposite of it right and if
you are not hungry and somebody just gives
you something to eat you just eat for the
sake of you know hey give me company and then
you go and eat some really bad food and things
like that so there is no immediate reward
apart from the company part of it but the
act of eating itself does not give you any
immediate reward but probably will have a
consequence in the long run Yeah right so
go eat some fried food just because your friend
asked you to eat will have consequences in
the in the long run right .
So rewards are iffy things right I mean so
we are going to make it very concrete right
I am going to say there is this some mechanism
in the environment that gives you a reward
but if you really think about it these rewards
are are everywhere right in fact the last
few years so Andy Barto was asking going around
asking this question where do rewards come
from right so when was he here 2009 yeah so
I hosted him here in 2009 and one of the talks
I mean at that time the talk he was going
around giving everywhere was where do rewards
come from okay so it was it is really an unforgettable
thing yeah.
So so this is not very clear so take it with
a pinch of salt when I say that the environment
is going to give you a reward signal, the
rewards could come from anywhere right in
fact it is not even clear what is the agent
what is the environment hmm so we have a lot
of Robotics guys here right suppose I am having
a robot learning problem right so what would
be the agent what would be the environment
the robot is the agent really okay let us
say I give you a navigation problem or a reaching
problem let us say I am trying to train a
robot to reach out and pick an object on the
table.
Environment is the workspace what about the
arm, what about the angle of the arm is it
in the environment or is it part of the agent
so where is the agent then so the arm is not
part of the agent the one controlling the
arm is the Agent so it becomes tricky right
we have to actually think about it is not
like okay as a robot the robot is a agent
everything outside the robot is the environment
right so it is not that boundaries are not
drawn as neatly around the physical entities
right suppose suppose let us consider forget
about robots let us say you are driving a
car okay so who is the agent what is the agent
and what is the environment there.
Right I mean always the right answer is depends
okay but but what does it depend on right
in this case the agent could be the car right
the environment could be the road right so
as a human being sitting and driving a car
you can look at okay what is the velocity
at which the car is moving okay and what is
the direction which the car is moving are
there pedestrians jumping in front of me right
and all those things right so this could be
your this could be your environment right
and the agent itself is the car you know I
am controlling the car on the other hand the
environment could include the car right and
the agent could be the human sitting there
and you can think of okay.
How much how much am I pushing my foot down
on the pedal which pedal should I be keeping
my feet on first case right and then should
I how much what torque should I apply to the
steering wheel right where should I be turning
my head to look at right should I be looking
at the mirror should I look at front right
or should I be looking down at my phone right
so all of these things decisions that you
have to make right while you are driving right
so there is this interface now the agent environment
interface becomes the human and the car right
or it could be even more right you can go
further back you can even go further back
into the human right thinking about okay which
okay I am talking about the motor cortex right.
So which neurons in my motor cortex should
fire now so that my arm twitches enough so
that I turn the wheel this much right so which
neurons should fire in my motor I mean the
autonomous nervous system so that my leg actually
pushes down with some kind of pressure right
so I could I could think of depending on the
kind of problem that I am solving right I
could think of drawing this agent environment
boundary anywhere right I mean not arbitrarily
anywhere but you can think of multiple places
where the same set of interacting entities
are there right but you have very different
kinds of modeling that you could do.
Okay it is not very clear when I say there
is an agent there is an environment do not
expect people to come and give you okay this
is the agent here is the environment now come
up with a reinforcement learning algorithm
that will solve this problem right so typically
you will have to think about this figure out
what is a right abstraction that you would
need right before you go start a solution
for this right so this is something which
you have to keep in mind nobody is giving
this to you apriori right so having said all
of this one other way of thinking about how
this interaction proceeds right.
So modulo all the caveats I have been giving
to you there is an agent okay it senses the
state of the environment it takes an action
okay and then that causes a change in the
state of the environment right so having said
all of this you can think of the interactions
as proceeding like this so I have St right
I sense that I take action At okay that causes
new state S t plus 1 and a reward so this
is a slight quark of the book itself right
where the reward corresponding to the state
and action at time t is labeled as R t plus
1 okay so this is a quirk in the book and
the reason they say is typically the next
state and the next reward are determined at
the same time.
And therefore it makes more sense to label
both of them with t plus 1 okay so one thing
here in the bandit case I was making a distinction
between n and t okay I am going back to using
t here but the t could be discrete time as
well in fact for most of the course t is going
to be discrete okay in fact t need not even
be time, t need not even be time okay so t
is steps so what are you talking about here
typically these are my decision epochs right
when I say t equal to 1 that means I am taking
my first decision when you say t equal to
2 that means I am taking my second decision
right this is typically okay.
Sometimes I am also interested in cases where
I do not take any decisions but the state
keeps changing over time but for most parts
when I say when I advance t by 1, that is
typically at the point where I am required
to take the next decision okay so later we
will actually look at a still a discrete-time
case but where decisions need not happen at
every time tick okay so we will look at that
case as well later but not immediately okay
for most part of it assume that t is a decision
tick ok not a time tick when t goes from t
to t plus 1, that means have taken another
decision the decisions could need not necessarily
take the same time.
For example consider the game of chess right
so each move that you make I mean so initially
you will be making moves very rapidly right
because you are playing from a standard opening
play or something and later on you actually
have to study the board position and then
you have to think about it and make moves
right but I still count each everything as
a single move right so you do not say the
first few moves were all count as one fourth
of a move each or anything because you did
it very fast so just exactly like that so
each move itself could take different amounts
of time right.
I am not worried about it and the intervals
at which you are asked to make decisions might
also be non-uniform I am not worried about
it okay this is the basic setting I am having
later when we talk about hierarchical RL we
will start worrying about the duration of
decisions if I take one action now how long
will it take for that action to complete and
those kinds of things we will worry about
later right now we are assuming that every
action takes the same time to complete so
time within quotes here okay.
So that is basically it this just keeps going
right so we will denote by S plus that distinguished
terminal state right so this just keeps going
until I reach S plus or it just keeps going
indefinitely if there is no distinguished
terminal state okay any questions so far,
the setup is clear right so what we are going
to do okay next thing I want to talk about
is the
reward itself so I am going to be very religiously
following chapter 3 in the book right and
I did ask people to read ahead to Chapter
three how many of you actually read chapter
three, four my god Subho you did you put your
hand up.
Okay then no that is not counted so 4 people
yeah sorry you are busy doing the assignments
is it hey release the assignments from chapter
3 as well so from now onwards what we will
do is before I start the chapter we will release
the assignments will that help written assignment
of course not the programming assignment yeah
so when is when is the second written assignment
due Friday is it so if you release some questions
today they will be able to finish it before
Friday night I only promised I will not release
it on Thursday.
Right I promised I will not release questions
on Thursday right I did not say anything about
Wednesday.. Varun is not giving any opinion
you were just thinking about okay they will
not do anything to him I am the one who will
get beaten up okay so we will extend the deadline
to Monday and then give them additional assignments
today yes so the people who read ahead so
what does the chapter say about reward functions
does it say anything about rewards yeah anything
else about the reward so classically reinforcement
learning assumes that the reward is a scalar
quantity alright so the rewards are
so the rewards are scalar and it is outside
the direct control of agent.
That is why I told you we put it in the environment
yeah we will come to that right so what does
that mean that the agent cannot arbitrarily
set the reward it has to do it through interaction
with the environment okay so that is essentially
the two main things that we need so the more
important thing here is the assumption that
the rewards are scalar right so what does
it mean it means is just a number right so
it might look that it is a pretty weak model
for the rewards but if you remember we talked
about a wide variety of applications of reinforcement
learning in the first lecture and in all of
those applications that we went through we
were actually looking at scalar robots.
Right so it does turn out that there is a
wide variety of settings where you can use
the scalar rewards and get away with it right
but there are cases where you might have to
make some kind of calls about trade-offs between
how much importance you want to give to one
event versus another so for example let us
again take the reaching tasks that we had
right so the so when I want to reach out to
an.. how would you set the rewards here
once I grasp it I will give a reward right
I can give you some reward like I can give
you a reward of 10 or something when I grasp
the yeah but then I need to optim..I need
to get there right.
So I what I am trying to do is optimize my
reward function if you remember the whole
problem in the reinforcement learning is to
well this is something I mentioned in the
very beginning the problem in RL is to behave
in such a way so that you get as much as reward
as possible in the long run right so if I
do not give you any reward function right
I will just be flailing around right I could
be happily moving waving my hand around not
doing anything with regard to grasping the
object right.
So I need to give some kind of a reward either
for grasping the object or how else would
you do this negative reward for every time
step I keep flailing around right it is like
you are in constant pain right and the pain
will stop once you hold this right because
the episode ends and you stop getting minus
ones there right so it is like somebody keeps
poking you with a pin all the time hmm keep
go go until you reach this is how we train
yeah any any any animal that draws a vehicle
right you keep pushing it in the side until
it actually reaches the destination right.
I mean humans are very cruel man I mean anyway
so that is how we do it right so but then
is that sufficient so you do not really want
to strain your hand right so I mean there
are joint limits right so you really do not
want to come up with a grasp grasp that looks
like this right this is also valid I have
caught the phone right so you do not want
to do that right you want to give some kind
of a.. you know additional pain right if I
do things like this right so if in fact for
me it actually was painful right but so you
want to do this communicate this to the bot
right how much additional pain do you give
it.
So grabbing this thing let us say gives you
a reward of 10 right and doing that gives
you a reward of say minus 100 so what is going
to happen you are going to be very cautious
right in trying to grab it right but if grabbing
this gives you a reward of 100 right and doing
that gives you a reward of minus point 1 right
you would still be cautious because I am being
optimal right so 99.1 is worse than 99.5 so
I will still be cautious about avoiding those
but I will not go to to significant extent
to do that because I am still getting my minus
1's right so the longer I take to get to the
get to a grasp right the more minus 1 I am
going to get right and the better form the
grasp is, the fewer minus point 1s I am going
to get.
So there is some trade-off I will form at
some point right but where the trade-off point
lies depends on the magnitude of the rewards
I am going to give you as well so if I am
going to give you a minus 1000 for doing something
like this right then I will be more careful
right so these are all trade-offs right when
you design the problem but so how do you set
these reward functions well understood problems
like grasping or reaching or robotics in general
right you can look at the problem that you
are trying to solve and try to figure out
okay which are the undesirable configurations
okay,
So very expensive robot so I do not want to
break it so let me make sure that all these
other things have a highly high negative values
right and versus a cheap robot or what I really
want to do is get there as soon as I can okay
do not mind throwing 300 robots at it because
each robot costs only 1 rupee right then I
can just not worry about crashing and burning
a few along the way right so it depends on
the domain right so there is still a significant
trade off that you will have to think about
right so even though I am saying it is a scalar
quantity there are instances where I will
have to kind of put multiple outcomes right
multiple outcomes on the same scale right
which makes it a little tricky just like in
this case I mean there is an outcome associated
with success which is grasping it and there
is outcome associated with well not really
failures but outcomes associated with undesirable
events along the way.
So I have to put all of these on the same
scale and I have to do it might have been
more convenient if you could have thought
of okay 100 for that ok, -minus 5 for this
but these are just things that you need to
avoid you know if there is some other way
I can communicate these things to robot then
that might be a better mechanism it turns
out it is hard to come up with an appropriate
optimization set up for doing this so the
scalar reward thing A is pretty powerful and
B kind of gels in some sense with how we also
do decision-making at the end of the day we
are very good at judging trade-offs right.
So whenever as soon as you start thinking
of doing these kinds of trade-offs in some
sense you are putting these on a same scale
right the putting them on the same scale because
they only then you can think about trade-offs
so in that way also it seems to be natural
and the third thing is having a single scalar
value makes it easier for us to optimize the
solution right we can always get a good optimal
solution this is for various reasons the scalar
values are fine right so I think that is one
of the homework questions which ask you to
think about scalar values a little bit more
I mean think and reason about it.
And so what else do we need the reward to
do well mathematically we need the rewards
to be bounded when we are talking about biological
systems that is not really a criterion because
I mean it has to be physical right so you
cannot have an unbounded neural spike in your
brain for corresponding to a reward right
so you may just fry your brain right so but
when talking about mathematical settings you
really want the reward to be bounded right
and so basically that is it so one other thing
later on we would like the rewards to be frequent
I will explain this later like once we start
looking at learning algorithms and stuff but
this essentially means that it should not
be that I get rewards say once in a million
time steps.
There is very little very limited literature
in this right so the one alternative which
people have explored is to look at vector-valued
rewards where each component of the reward
corresponds to a different thing that you
want to achieve and these are called typically
multi-criteria RL right there are very few
papers maybe five or six papers out there
which talk about multi criterion reinforcement
learning in fact there is a corresponding
optimization thing also called multi-criterion
optimization right.
So where people talk about different notions
of optimality even so what exactly is optimal
right so optimal is where the objective function
you reach a minima of the objective function
but now if you are going to look at it in
multiple dimensions so you may end up reaching
some kind of saddle points also right so what
exactly is the optima in this case so people
talk about those kinds of characterization.
So there is more work in multi-agent settings
in looking at more richer reward functions
than in single agent RL right yeah very little
out there and it will be interesting to come
up with some kind of qualitative feedback
as well instead of looking at this kind of
a quantitative feedback and if you like that
kind of work there are there is some kind
of work in fuzzy RL where the feedback signal
is a fuzzy signal not much again very little
and there is one more thing I want to mention
yeah but all of those are scalar I mean there
are all kinds of work on like instead of looking
at the reward but look at the perception of
reward and so on so forth.
But all of these are still scalar quantities
and they are not vector valued quantities
but it is a much richer notion of feedback
than what you would is typically a reward
function yeah so what we mean by frequent
is that you should not be getting rewards
like once in a million time steps or something
then you will never learn anything right you
are trying to optimize rewards and regardless
of what you do for a million time steps you
get nothing right that is too long a horizon
for you to learn anything over right so typically
you expect more reward to come to you along
the way okay.
So that is what is rewards
so policy so what is it so I am just talking
about different components of a reinforcement
learning system okay so we talked about states
and actions right basically the agent and
the environment now you're talking about the
reward okay the next thing you want to talk
about is the policy so what is the policy
no 0 is non informative right I really cannot
change my unless I have gotten a minus 1 somewhere
I do not know if zero is good or bad right
I mean I really cannot change anything based
on 0 but that is a good point yeah.
So when we say frequent rewards I do mean
frequent non zero rewards right so we know
what a policy is right all of us know what
policies are so what is a policy
so I am going to denote a policy as this as
a conditional thing from now on so what is
this is essentially the probability that right
the probability that at time t the agent will
take action a given that at time t the state
is small s.
So ideally I should have a t there right so
pi t of a, s is a probability that at time
t I will take action a given that at time
t the state was s okay so normally for most
of the material that we cover right I will
be looking at what are known as stationary
policies so what is a stationary policy right
a stationary policy is something which is
essentially
so regardless of the value of t I will be
using the same probability so the probability
that let us say my state is 1 right probability
that when give me some other symbol to use
as state let us say my state is l okay I do
not think I used l for anything so far right
we have in the proofs you use l or is it yeah
let us say okay fine let us use it one then
people can all of you are smart enough to
figure out this right.
So let us say state is 1 right so I do not
care whether it is 1 that time one whether
s1 is equal to 1 or s 25 is equal to 1 the
probability that I will take action A1 will
be the same right the probability I will take
action A2 will be the same so essentially
what I am saying is.
Probability that A1 equal to a1 given S1 equal
to 1 is equal to probability that something
like this okay right so this is what I mean
by stationary that is what I am saying here
so if I want to explicitly talk about non-stationary
policies okay I will use the pi t notation
okay if I am talking about stationary policies
I will just use the pi notation.
Okay so what is my policy the what is the
goal in trying to come up with a policy no
see we have not even gone there right I am
just defining things right a non-stationary
policy is just a collection of functions collection
of probability distributions one for each
time step right a stationary policy is a single
well it is actually also a set of probability
distributions one for each state right a non
stationary policy is a collection of such
sets one for each time step as well as one
for each state that is basically it how you
derive how you derive a non-stationary policy
or how you learn it from data and other things
they are independent questions I am just talking
about its simple definition of the quantity
when you learn your goal should be a stationary
policy right the end goal can be a stationary
policy but if you have a stationary policy
there is no subsequent learning we will come
to that right so there are different time
scales at which you can learn right.
So I can have a stationary policy run the
full episode using the stationary policy and
then take the rewards I get and then use that
to update my parameters and come up with a
new stationary policy right so these times
I am talking about the t here is essentially
the index over a single interaction okay I
am not talking about multiple interactions
over the single interaction right suppose
I start from some S0 I come and end at S plus
over that interaction my policy stays fixed
that seems to be a reasonable assumption right.
So you could think of having states learning
a sequence of stationary policies so what
is my goal in learning a policy here is to
learn something that will maximize the reward
that I get right but not individually but
something that will maximize it in the long
run okay so what do I mean by that suppose
I am riding a cycle right so suppose you leave
your hands and say they look at me or something
like that might give you a temporary kick
you know I feel really good about myself but
then you might the next minute you might ram
into another vehicle or a tree or a building
whatever right and get injured right.
So that is something that gives you a well
depends but hopefully that is something that
will deter you from doing crazy things on
a cycle the next time around right so the
short-term reward was just feeling good about
you for one minute and the long term penalty
was getting into a crash or whatever right
so these kinds of things are odd or even simple
things like in chess you know the first thing
kids they try to capture the Queen and whole
bunch of other things and then as a result
end up losing the game right so these kinds
of things ok so do not look for short-term
rewards you should look for something that
maximizes your rewards in the long term.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved